Guide to the Herbert Gold papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Herbert Gold Papers,
1951-1984.
Gold, Herbert, 1924-
1 linear ft (2 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0494
4079721
This collection contains personal and professional correspondence to and from Herbert Gold, and manuscripts and proofs of his written works, from 1951-1984.
Biographical Note
Jewish-American novelist Herbert Gold was born in Cleveland, Ohio on March 9th, 1924. Gold is the first of five children; his father, Samuel Gold, was a Russian immigrant who struggled to adjust to his life in America. Gold is well known for his novels, short stories, and literary articles, but during his early career he also studied and taught philosophy.
Herbert Gold began writing in elementary school, and later he wrote for the school newspaper at Lakewood High School. Shortly after high school, Gold attended Columbia University to study philosophy, but his education was interrupted from 1942-1946 when he served in the United States Army. After graduating from Columbia in 1946, Gold traveled to Paris to continue his study of philosophy on a Fulbright scholarship; it was during this time that Gold completed his first novel, Birth of a Hero. Gold returned to Cleveland in 1951 to teach philosophy at the Western Reserve University until 1953.
In addition to over 20 novels, Gold has published numerous short stories and articles that have appeared in both popular and literary magazines. His autobiography, My Last Two Thousand Years, was published in 1972. Gold wrote about his country, his Jewish heritage, and the beat movement; common themes in his work include American identity, power, money, and sex. His works were both praised and ridiculed. Herbert Gold traveled a lot, and lived in Haiti, Detroit, Ohio, and New York. He eventually settled down in San Francisco, where he currently resides. Gold was married twice, and is a father of 5, and a grandfather of 6.
Scope and Content
The Herbert Gold Collection consists of correspondence and manuscript drafts. Most of the correspondence is between Gold and his editor, Seymour Lawrence between 1951 and 1960. However, letters to and from Gold and various persons are also included. Seven manuscript drafts, summaries, and proofs are located in this collection.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 2 series. Materials in each folder are arranged chronologically:
Series I. Correspondence, 1951-1967, Undated
Series II. Manuscripts, 1955-1984
Subjects
Gold, Herbert, 1924-; Lawrence, Seymour, 1926-1996.; American literature--20th century.; Novelists, American--20th century.; Articles.; Essays.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts.; Proofs.; Authors, American.; Essayist.; Journalists.; Novelists, American.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1969 M-1969 Gold, Herbert Gift
Gift of the author, 1969.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1951-1967, Undated
  Series I primarily contains correspondence between Gold and his editor, Seymour Lawrence, between 1951 and 1960. It was during this time that Lawrence worked for Gold's publisher, Little, Brown, and Co. Although some of the correspondence is personal, the majority relates specifically to the writing, publication, and review of his written works. Among letters from Seymour Lawrence are letters from Nancy Reynolds, Gold's copy editor, Saul Bellow, Robert Brustein, Herbert Gold, Merle Miller, Mark Schorer, and Mark Van Doren. In addition to these letters, folder 1 contains correspondence concerning litigation (1965) in regard to Harry Bridges, the International Longshore and Warehouse Union (ILWU), and the Longshore Jobs Defense Committee, the latter of which Gold was a member.
  - Correspondence Concerning Litigation, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lawrence, Seymour, 1951, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lawrence, Seymour, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reynolds, Nancy, 1955-1957, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Various Correspondence to Gold, 1961-1963, 1967-1969, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Various Correspondence from Gold, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Manuscripts, 1955-1984
  There are 7 manuscript titles in this collection: Fathers, The Man Who Was Not With It, The Optimist, Salt, Song for Saroyan, Therefore Be Bold, and William Saroyan, Still in the Woods. Also within this series is a 1984 Banana Republic Travel and Safari Clothing Catalog containing an article by Gold; and an article entitled "Truth and Falsity in the Novel," reprinted from the 1956 Hudson Review. There are 3 copies of Fathers in this series: galley proofs 1 and 2, and the master set and plate proof. A summary and a trade editorial report exists for The Man Who Was Not With It, rather than a full manuscript draft. There are manuscript and published copies of Song for Saroyan, as well as an interview with Saroyan and miscellaneous correspondence regarding its publication.
  - Banana Republic Travel and Safari Clothing Catalog, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fathers--Gallery Proof 1, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Fathers--Gallery Proof 2, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Fathers--Master Set, Plate Proof, 1966 (Box 3)
  - The Man Who Was Not With It--Summery, Trade Editorial Report, Summery, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Optimist--Setting Copy, Cover, Parts 1 and 2, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Optimist--Setting Copy, Part 3, pages 137-342, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Optimist--Setting Copy, Part 3, pages 343-477, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Salt--Chapters 1-3, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Salt--Chapters 4-9, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Song for Saroyan--Manuscript and Published Copies, Interview With Saroyan, Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1979, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Therefore Be Bold--Chapters 1-9, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Therefore Be Bold--Chapters 10-19, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - “Truth and Falsity in the Novel”--Reprinted from the Hudson Review volume 8, number 3, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - William Saroyan, Still in the Woods, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 21)